this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Felina for SE radio I'm
here today with two guests I'm the
founder who and Marian Petri Marian
Petri studies how people reason and
communicate about design and problem
solving and how to use representations
in their reasoning she's a professor of
computing at the Open University in the
UK and she holds degrees in
psycholinguistics and computer science
we also have here and right Vander Hoek
he's a programmer who loves to create
new tools that help developers be more
effective effective and efficient he's a
professor of informatics at the
University of California and holds
degrees in business oriented computer
science and computer science welcome to
the show to the both of you thank you
thank you very much excited to be here
so you just wrote a book about software
design and that book is going to be the
core of this episode we're really
interested in what the book offers but
first I want to talk a little bit about
software design because it's it's this
vague abstract thing so I'm curious what
is software design for you well I think
we need to distinguish a little bit
between design and designing so a lot of
what we're actually researching is
designing and talking about design not
just the design so we tend to think
about design is the thing that governs
the the plan the thing that governs the
structure and the behavior of the
software but what we're studying is
designing behavior which is how people
think about that plan and how they
create that structure how they have
dialogues about it how they how they
move it along how they innovate and so
on and so that whole business about
design thinking is at the core of what
we do you know I think design designing
and the design that eventually is
produced right so so what is design has
changed over time as it's a phase in the
life cycle something that we do it's
something that's throughout the life's
ichael for us design is really something
that developers do throughout I'm
designing my requirements right I'm not
just eliciting them I'm actually
designing them with the people that I'm
working with designing my architecture
I'm actually designing the
implementation I'm designing the test
cases because the kinds of ways that I'm
working are designedly ways of working
it across all of those and so so what we
we like to do is actually take all of
soft engineering all of software
development as a design exercise from
beginning to end and that's kind of the
lens that we've been using towards
towards everything that we look at
pretty much interesting so eliciting
requirements is usually I don't think
it's usually seen as a design activity
does that activity change if you look at
it as a design activity rather than as a
interviewing observing getting the
requirements activity I think it's it
doesn't necessarily change for everybody
but the awareness of it being a design
kind of activity changes what you can
bring to it right so an element is
indeed figuring out you know what people
have to say and what they think they
might need what they think they might
want but then the other part of it is
also we're contributing we're part of a
conversation right if you and I are
working on a software system and I am
interviewing you trying to figure out
what you need it's not uncommon for us
to go through the whiteboard and draw
something out okay and at that point
we're actually no longer sort of trying
to pry out of your brain what we're
doing but we're collectively shaping
what the software system is going to be
in the end right and and so for us
design is a lot about building a plan
but the plan also has some parameters to
it and a key parameter is that once it's
realized it better satisfy two
stakeholders and and that's something
that you see for design in architecture
that's something that you see for design
in buildings that's something that you
see in design for fashion is equally so
in software generic so so by putting on
that lens you know we sort of give
everybody the freedom to contribute to
what the shape of their software system
in the end
is yes so you're saying we want to give
everyone a chance to contribute does
that also mean you don't see a designer
or an architect as a separate rolling a
team everyone all the developers maybe
even the user interface developer Center
database admins are they all designing
are they old designers they are all
participating right and and they I think
there's there certainly separate roles
an architect is going to shape the
structure of the system that's what they
do it's kind of they're gonna figure out
what the main components are but when
you think about the design of the
software system you know somebody who is
designing a piece of the user interface
if they do this wrong it can seriously
influence the usability of the system
right and and how that system is going
to be accepted I'm and and I think I'm
gonna tell a little story because I
think that that might illustrate it a
little bit right he loves so now I do
like stories so one of the pairs of
designers that we talked to and observed
and one was a user interface designer
and that's what they did
one was an architect and what would
happen is we asked the question so user
interface designer right we know the
methods that you use right you user
studies you interview people you build
personas and everything else so the what
degree are you actually aware of the
architecture and and vice versa and it
turns out that the user interface person
is deeply aware of the architecture
because the architecture is distributed
and there are some data that is over
here some dated that it's over there and
some things that's over here and in this
case a she she was aware because there
were certain things that she wanted to
build there were certain reports that
she wanted to design for the users that
she couldn't because it would involve
too much data transfer from one to the
other and so that's where constraints
from one level of design play in the
other parts of design and so what would
happen is she would request can the
architecture be redesigned so I can
built this report and that that's why I
view everybody contributing to the
design because everybody is in the end
making decisions that
that determined whether in the end the
people actually gonna like the software
yes or no right that's an
oversimplification we're gonna like it
but what it meets the needs whether the
stakeholders are satisfied but there's
another layer to that which is that if
all of the people involved are doing
their jobs effectively they're thinking
about design they're doing design
thinking whether or not the design is
there named responsibility so what is
that design thinking can you give a
definition for that I don't think it's
easy to define it per se but it's a
process of understanding that there is a
relationship between the way we
understand the problem and the way that
we understand the solution and thinking
continually repeatedly reflectively
about those definitions in that
relationship so I mean this is the sort
of thing that that Michael Jackson was
getting on with problem frames and what
we're seeing that played out in is every
level of software development all the
way through maintenance because the
question is hang on a minute why is why
is code the way it is why is this
software the way it is it was this way
to solve a set of problems where he had
a set of priorities we made some did we
make those decisions how can we we can
pull back that rationale to make sense
of what's here and how we can improve it
or how we can make it do something new
or something additional you made a brief
reference there to Michael Jackson and
the problem frames I'm not sure if
everyone in the audience is familiar
were there can you maybe elaborate I'm
not sure if I can
so Michael Jackson is an eminent it's a
consultant and and and theorist in in
our area he also happens to be a
visiting professor at the Open
University he's done a number of books
about software development about ways of
thinking about software development over
the years and one of them is called
problem frames and it is very much about
making explicit thinking about the
relationship between what we understand
the problem to be and what we understand
the solution to be and and thinking
about solutions in terms of problems all
the time as a dialogue great thanks
goodnight can I add one bit sure I'm so
design thinking for a number of people
has a somewhat narrow interpretation I'm
so if you think about
especially in the field of HCI and in
the field of design overall design
thinking is is partly a mindset and it's
partly also a nomer for a particular
approach which is we all pile in the
room we do a whole bunch of
brainstorming and five days later
magically we have a design that's that's
not how we actually interpret Design
Thinking in in our view Design Thinking
for us is the mindset inside all of the
individuals in the organization just
being aware that the choices we are
making always impact what might happen
next and so so putting the designers
head on for the architect is normal
because that's what they do but also for
the programmer and also for the person
designing the test cases right it's what
is the impact of what I'm doing on the
software on the design of this on the
design of the software absolutely on the
behavior and the eventual thinks that
might happen maybe I'll try to give
another example most organizations when
you think of the architect and designers
they play a key role I have examples of
organizations where individuals who then
subsequently have to program something
made certain choices right so think
about it for instance the the report
that I need to create that is based on a
lot of data that's there and so I as a
user you know press give me the report
and the typical way in which a
programmer might actually program this
is send a query to the database database
computes the results since the results
back and this is a local health care
company this is the way they programmed
it and they put it in there then they
put it out there and then guess what
happened there were a lot of Records and
so the user pressed the button and it
took a few seconds and then it took
longer and then it took longer because
there were more records and then they
started thinking about so how are the
different ways of doing it then they
figured out that hey there is a design
pattern actually turns out there is a
design pattern where you sent the query
you get the first bits of results back
you populate your screen the user is
happy because the screen actually
already has a results and in the
background you obtain the rest of the
results so that they scroll down you you
have the seamless experience and so
you've just eliminated
two three four five seconds of waiting
time on somebody that's not the
architect right that's also not the user
interface designer
it's a programmer yeah who is making
these kinds of decisions and that's what
we're talking about can you can you put
your design head on because ultimately
the kinds of choices that you make in
your program again become visible or not
to the people that are using it Thanks
so I think what your book is about it's
also design thinking right so the book
so far design decoded has 66 ways in
which expert designers think is that do
you think those 66 tips are everything
that you need to know is it at least
Bartosz fert becoming a good designer
what the book is about is it just so
we've spent decades researching
high-performing teams expert software
developers and other software developers
in industry doing real salt real problem
solving and what the book is an attempt
to do is to distill the research results
that identify the traits that experts
have the behaviors that they display
that distinguish them from the less
high-performing teams it isn't about the
technical knowledge that they have
because that's covered elsewhere it's
much more about in effect the design
behaviors the design practices they have
that keep them reflective that unites
their team around design thinking that
drive them to innovation and in in some
ways that that mitigate against the
kinds of biases that we we have in our
thinking inherently so it's distillation
of those distinguishing behaviors
practices approaches that that are in
the book it's very much about design
name rather than about design yes yes
yes and to answer your question in
slightly different way by no means is
the book complete that there is a test
that we used in the book and for any
insight to be included it needed to have
been documented and studied somewhere in
the literature right so
than this being a book where we said
this is what we think happens by which
you see in many books it is great
because we have many classic books that
are exactly of that nature of you know
here's a reflection on how I work Steve
McConnell you know etc this book we
wanted to go a little deeper and
actually be able to back up with proof
they or another evidence data that these
things actually in fact do happen and
that that it's documented somewhere and
so I have a you know my poor
brother-in-law he he is a software
engineer you develop software and he
said I you know of course the first
thing I did was put drafts of the book
in front of him and he said there's
another one there's another one you know
expert software designers they ship they
ship their software and we kind of know
that that's true but in the end I had to
sort of tell them well we can't put us
in here because we can't find an actual
paper or you know study that says here's
how this plays out here's how we know
that this is true and here's why that
matters so by no means it's complete but
it is it does get at the core of what it
means to think and I think that that's
something that has been playing out a
lot in the in the academic literature of
studying software designers all the way
going back to the 70s and 80s oh when we
start talking about opportunistic versus
rationalistic design thinking you know
we go deep or we go broad line yeah and
it turns out those were some of the
initial papers and we've gotten a much
more refined understanding since then
that actually experts both go deep and
go broad but adjust when they do this
right so if it turns out that I have a
difficult issue at hand they might go
very deep very quickly and not sort out
the whole problem as a whole and two
examples there if you think of how
eclipse was developed I do is four
people piled themselves in a room much
like where we are today whiteboards
everywhere plus a bunch of computers and
so they talked on the whiteboards and
then they program things up that was
going as deep as needed to make sure for
themselves that they understood what
they were thinking about actually would
work
and once they had that they stepped back
and brought into design to include the
other parts so they focused on it on a
particularly important part of the
software that they didn't know for sure
they could sort out and sorted it out as
deep as need in some other cases you
have to go much broader first but you
have to really understand all the
stakeholders you have to really
understand what the needs are and in
such cases you might not program first
so it depends a lot on the proton on the
the kind of design problem that you're
facing how the experts take their their
little tool bag and start approaching
figuring things out start approaching
where do I might want to make my
progress first great
so to summarize all the tips in your
book are all evidence-based they all
come from research either your own
research or other people's research it's
not just things that are your opinion
it's things that are grounded in
research and even though the book
doesn't have the list of all the papers
the companion website that we also will
link to in the show notes has all the
background research so if people are
really interested in reading the papers
they can find that on the companion
website absolutely cool so why was this
book needed because the both of you
already mentioned that you've been
working on this for a long time why now
what was the need well one of the things
that we miss in our discipline is theory
and I think if I've been striving toward
anything over the decades that I've been
doing research it's a theory of
expertise and software design so we
haven't done there yet but it's an
attempt to consolidate what we
understand about expertise into one
place because most of the books that
already do that are personal reflections
not evidence-based reflections on what
happens in practice and at the same time
there's an awful lot of literature by
other people who are for example
proposing alternative methods or we have
different perspectives that take a very
different view on this and a lot of
literature that comes out for example
that practitioners object to is
prescriptive about methods and this
isn't about prescription this is just
about holding up a mirror to expert
practice and saying what is it that you
do can we see the patterns across
different people can we understand what
the characteristics are that lead to
you know ships on within budget on time
no loud brown smells and and and try to
bring that into into some kind of
coherence it also matters to be able to
articulate these to help teach them so
one of the nice things there's an awful
lot of taken for granted knowledge in
expert practice if you happen to be in
one of those high-performing teams you
probably get integrated into that
culture and and you learn through
experience but what about for other
people so the notion that you can
actually articulate some of us and give
people things to think about in their
own practice things to improve and
things to respect in their own practice
because where our hope is that actually
lots of people who recognize these
things say yes I do that I wonder if I
do it enough or I could help somebody
else do that that articulation is part
of what we're trying to to achieve at
the book I really like that because lots
of the tips in the book make total sense
right for example one of them is experts
keep it simple oh that makes so much
sense do we even need to write it down
but you're so right by articulating it
you can also start reflecting on it
isn't this simple enough and who in my
team is a little bit better at that and
might need some help
to get at a different level so even if
it seems totally logical everything
that's there it resonated with me a lot
I see how it's very valuable to have it
written that somewhere so that you can
talk about you actually put your finger
in something that's been really
interesting because the book has has had
a somewhat polarizing response in the
sense that there's some people that read
it and they go these are great I'm gonna
put that you know I'm gonna print them
out and I'm gonna put them on the wall
they'll help me remember and then there
are some people who say these are
obvious yeah of course you you just put
those away but the interesting thing to
us is that when we go into the
organizations and we for instance
observe the developers at work which is
one of the things that we do right we
will go in we'll sit in on a meeting
they're designing at the whiteboard or
designing at their screen or they're you
know having a meeting and when we
observe is really interesting that is
the people who say this is valuable
because it helps me remember that
actually have a practice of bringing the
the things that you were talking about
like keep it simple into the
conversation we recently were at a major
organization observe their design is
working and every five minutes and
throughout the entire conversation it
was is this simple enough do we need
this complexity why are we introducing
this and it was very very conscious in
the conversation of these designers and
we've run some experiments where we've
compared expert designers versus novice
designers and when you see the behavior
differences these kinds of questions of
keep it simple don't appear in the
novice conversations even though they're
very well aware that they're meant to
keep it simple they get lost in the
design itself and they forget to stand
there and reflect on what they're doing
and that's the difference that's there
that that's why and again that's why the
book brings a vocabulary out and a way
of externalizing the kinds of things
that we might be doing and now to turn
that around and bringing that into our
meetings experts know intuitively to do
some of these but giving everybody the
option to do that and everybody the
option to actually say hey have we
thought about the right constraints are
there assumptions that might you know be
violated later on that we're resting on
right now that we should actually
resolve right now rather than later
those are the kinds of lessons in sides
tips in the book that's that will make a
difference if you bring them into your
practice yeah I think that goes back to
what Maryann was saying that some people
are in a high-performing team and
everything works well but they don't
really know why and then maybe if they
switch teams they don't know what
lessons to take away from a
high-performing team and this might also
give some handsome feet to that idea
like oh this is what we're doing this is
what we're doing so if I start my own
team if we're starting my own company
these are the things that I'm going to
take away well it's interesting because
I would actually clarify a little bit
that one of the things that
distinguishes high-performing teams is
they do have these
socially reinforcing practices that keep
drawing them to design thinking that
keep and that and as they draw new
people into the team they assimilate
them into these practices and it's very
reflective they talk about them they
think about them so one of the responses
we've had from practitioners in industry
about the book is this is an opportunity
for us to talk about design thinking
with some of our people who don't know
about talking about design thinking and
so they've actually brought us in to use
the book to leverage conversations about
designing converse and to try to use the
book as I as the beginning of a
vocabulary about design thinking in
software so that people can begin to
talk about how they're going about
things what assumptions they're making
what they do in their process compare it
with other people and begin to build a
culture of design thinking that isn't
just isolated people going away and
coding quietly or pairs going away and
falling into their particular practices
but are about building a much more
general view on thinking about design I
think the final thought maybe is there's
also a lot of folklore and myth around
expert designers right so if you've been
around for thirty years and you've built
all the experience then you know you
you're an expert and naturally you're a
gifted designer versus naturally or not
the book gives sort of a glimpse that
that some of those pieces might not be
true and and one of the again stories is
when we were doing some of the research
on a Neath the book we we went to a
number of companies and said can we have
some of your best architecture designers
for a couple hours and can we can we
have them do design work for a little
while and so we went to one company that
that went to another company and their
third company this really young kid
comes out and so my gratitude and I were
sitting there looked at each other with
you know the stereotypical which we made
our own mistake right like it is the one
who's because it really this is the one
you know okay you know they gave us
somebody because the others must have
been busy and then they started
designing and we witness and when it's a
piece of beauty the person knows exactly
what they're doing
and so afterwards we talked to him and
said how right but what happened he said
well I made sure in in my school that I
every project I did I focused on the
design component I took all the classes
where I could design some software and
it could make lots of mistakes and so he
had it in himself to choose the path
that encountered many of the things that
are heat that are in the book
in some ways consciously and on his own
trying to figure out what was there I
mean he was an outstanding designer as a
result and the book gives sort of the
ability for others to say can I where
can I put this into practice but the
other insight is that we tend to think
about experts and others as though they
are discrete categories and the truth is
that experts do not always exhibit
expert behaviors and novices sometimes
exhibit expert behaviors and it's not as
discrete as that so I had a student
tomorrow Lopez who did work on errors
and recovery from error during the
course of software development and one
of the things that was fascinating was
that expert developers with incredible
track records we're leaving in their
code what looked like novice bugs and
the question is are they idiots and the
cancer is of course they're not the
truth is that they know that what they
really want to do is keep focused on
their destination and to build something
and they know they have a very well
embedded safety net for catching all of
those bugs downstream and so if you look
at the more the broader psychological
literature you find that experts make
more slips than non experts because they
don't have to do that continual
self-monitoring because they know that a
they will reach their destination and
having done so they can do their
clean-up process and that that will be
reliable and so there are these
interesting artifacts that you get and
one of the the really powerful things
that that's in the book one of my
favorite insights is about how error how
experts deal with and the attitude to
error so experts make slips but they're
not afraid of making slips if they if
they find an error in their code instead
of saying oh no they say oh that's
interesting why is that does it occur
anywhere else
might lead us to understand about our
assumptions and so they use it as a form
of exploration and then they create an
environment around them where the same
thing applies so let's innovate
let's try things but we also know that
we're all so good that we're paying
attention so that if we get it wrong
we'll spot it and we'll be able to fix
it we'll be able to learn from that so
it's actually quite one of the surprises
has been this business that you don't
just assume that if you do this you will
be expert or if you don't do this you
aren't expert but that we see evidence
of expert behavior this kind of
reflective open-minded innovative
practice at different levels and it's
really about the consistency and it's
really about the ability to pull back
into the highest standards of design
thinking on a regular basis not about it
being there every single second so I'm
very interested in this story about this
young designer that was really good at
designing already it makes me think of
what can we do to become better
designers and I think what you were
saying in the story of that young person
that it's very much about deliberate
practice so he chose exercises that were
a little bit above his level and then he
advanced if you want to be a better
designer how would you do that because
you're gonna learn a new programming
language you can practice on your own
with small exercises and you can get
better but what type of suppose I want
to take a day week for a while to be a
better designer what type of things do I
deliberately practice that's a great
question
there's a variety of things that you can
do so so one of the one of the things
that we know experts do is they actually
go look at other systems and and they do
exactly what you said right there
they're doing their business they're
there they're working hard they're
designing things and then they have a
couple of hours and they say you know
there's this new open-source system I've
heard about let me just go look and so
they go to get help and pull down the
code and they study the code for a while
and that's one of the ways in which they
broaden the knowledge and they they look
at the patterns that others hues and
they look at the solution strategies
that other use so that's one part that
you can do is to simply actually examine
existing systems if you are a young
student right and you want you want to
figure out more a great way to deal with
this is to participate in open source
software and it will take you a while
first you make a little tiny bug fix but
as you become more familiar it is an
opportunity for you to practice to
become maybe part of closer to the core
team to become a trusted contributor to
eventually maybe become a core team
member we have had a number of students
at UCI into my University who a number
of years back all were contributing to
HTTP the web apache and they sought out
again the challenge of doing so and as a
result that they have these awesome jobs
right now
maybe so so one of them is now at minor
league baseball and re-architecting the
entire streaming service partly because
they had the experience of becoming part
of the team that Apache and partly
because one of the other students that
you know key you fix this little bug
right and so seeking out how you can
challenge yourself in the open source
world as a student it's one way to do it
and then insight you know the commercial
world talk to your manager you know ask
ask for the next design challenge or ask
whether you can witness the team working
ask whether you can be part of it
because and and good managers actually
will encourage that right they will
already walk you down that path to
challenge you on that way but if you
don't feel like you're getting enough
you certainly should or you should talk
to the architect and say the architect
actually has needs one of the architects
that you may know we're up on all
meringue over at Phillips he redesigned
the product line for the Phillips TVs
because they realized that writing the
software for scratch from each of the
TV's becomes a little difficult
and so what they and what he designed he
product line but when I talked to him
what did he really do well he took
showers he walked he used the whiteboard
I mean all the classical things yeah
then he came into the office and said
you can you come to the whiteboard with
me and would draw on the whiteboard his
architecture and in explaining he would
learn what he didn't know but at the
same time if I am the person who he
pulls in I might be learning how he
thinks right and he did that not once he
did it twice he did it three times and
so so so there's kind of two sides to
the story one is you could put yourself
in the position to be somebody who
listens and if you give the right kind
of feedback he's gonna pull you in more
often yeah and the other side their
story is look at the practice that that
he had which was to explicitly pull in
others and force himself to explain what
he was doing because it is important for
you to externalize what's going on
inside your head and the drawings are
one thing but the verbalization of it is
another nice I like it how I could
already recognize four of your insights
from the book in that story so you had
experts borrow for looking at open
source experts collaborate for working
together with your team experts sketch
for being on the whiteboard and experts
take breaks for you know walking and
going in a shower I really love how the
vocabulary if the book is now in my
brain of course because I read it three
times home for the last it's very much
in my brain so it I mean I'm really
feeling that it works like I recognized
all these trades and I could now
recognize them in teams or in other
people and and to just go back to to rob
for just a second in some ways he be
partly was an inspiration for what's in
here because he was one of the very
first people that I talked to and
started asking so how do you do this
because part of my challenge is I have
to teach undergraduates how to design
and at the University one way in which
we tend to do that is to we first teach
them about requirements engineering in a
course and then they have a document and
then we teach them about the notation of
design except you Mel or some other
other notation and then we kind of set
them home and say go design for a while
and in three weeks you hand in your
design and we'll grade it and I felt
deeply unsatisfied about there's nothing
I can tell them about how they should
behave what kind of steps they might be
able to
and there are sort of these structure
design methods that you can apply but
then your foot you're following a
formula right and that's not always
going to get you where you need to be so
so I started talking to people like
Robin others to say what are you doing
and then starting to ask the question
what can I bring into the classroom so
that the students start understanding
what they need to work on and and I just
have to tell one because when you ask
about favourites and that this totally
is my favorite right
experts focus on the essence so experts
are not afraid of solving the hard part
of the design problem in hand and if you
are in your typical software engineering
class and you give a design problem your
students are working on the user
interface the login screen you know how
which database we might be able to use
and and they're staying as far and as
long away as possible away from where is
the hard part right and so so to be able
to now go into my classroom insight
we're kind of design the hard part
that's what we're gonna do first and
you're gonna do that every single time
and eventually they start getting that
actually yes you're right because many
design problems unfold themselves over
time right and if I don't get to the
unfolding part in time it's gonna be
really night night the day before I need
to hand in my assignment right so that's
that's where the challenge is and and
being able to now bring that into the
classroom based on everything that we
found that's changing how how we're
teaching them and and I think that's you
know our ultimate hope is that that that
kind of teaching can can translate to
other universities and other places as
well because that's that's again when
you go back to how can I learn I think
there's also an obligation on us
teachers to actually bring bring this
kind of knowledge about how
professionals do their job into the
classroom but there's a resonance with
the focus on the essence and innovation
as well so it isn't it is understanding
that you you deal with the hard stuff
first but also if you're going to make
an innovation step you want to make it
about that essence and you want to make
it before every other piece that you've
designed is going to constrain away your
ability
to make it differently and so that that
shift of perspective and where people
put their attention first and where they
invest their attention is actually quite
important so one of the the observations
about experts as experts put a lot more
effort upfront before they get into
implementation and novices jump into
implementation for good reason it's fine
as part of that sort of development of
skill but the understanding that it's
okay we'll have time to write code but
let's think hard about what it is that
we want to do and so if you're watching
teams we did some work a long time ago
on programmers mental imagery an awful
lot of what's going on is is code is
pretty much only limited by what people
can imagine right we're not limited by
physical materials and even the
technology on which we're building is
open to our expansion as we develop new
technology and one of the things about
mental imagery is how are these people
who are very extraordinary innovators
what is it that they do in their minds
where are they putting in their
attention and then how are they
communicating that and as I'm listening
to Andre tell the story about the
whiteboard and the retailer that's
exactly what happens so I did a study
where I asked people to solve a given
problem and I watched them and I asked
them I didn't actually ask them to think
aloud but occasionally if they do things
that they stand they sit cross their
legs with a pad of paper and they wave
their hand over the pad of paper
nothing gets written down or they wave
their hand in the air or they look into
the corner of the room and their eyes
move at that point I would say to them
what do you see or what does it smell
like or what color is it but what was
very interesting is just so they're
clearly generating mental images that
they are not externalizing in that
moment at the point when it congeals
when it becomes coherent to them very
often my favorite story is it guys at
that point said excuse me a minute put
his empty notepad down ran out of the
room down the corridor and said I've got
the solution and started drawing a
solution on the whiteboard because what
he had done was solved the essence of a
problem by analogy he was talking about
an interesting networking problem and it
had to do
with how they were making transfers
across the wall to make sure that
everything that crossed some kind of
boundary had the right properties he
draws us up for everybody everybody
interrogate the design and then he came
back and sat down and said where was I
shall we can it kept me on but that
whole business about coming into the
hard part
recognizing the resonances in the the
essential challenges between the
distribut I had set him and a problem he
was trying trying to solve in his own
work and then expressing that through
some kind of imagery on the whiteboard
and starting the design discussion was
absolutely classic expert behavior and
then as I studied that team over time
that image was redrawn a hundred times
and interrogated a hundred times and be
it continued to be the focal image for
that project because that was the
essence of the solution even though
there was an enormous amount of
technical tale that followed from that
and so that that business about where
people put their attention and that
focus on the essences is very very
resonant across the piece but of course
if you are a young program or student
it's hard to know what the essence is if
you've got I thinking of my own project
course for first-year students into
Delft
you give them a problem and they think
the hardest part is picking the database
because they they have never solved the
problem like this so part of being
expert and part of solving the hard part
first is of course also knowing what the
hard part is is this also something that
you can practice or is that really a
matter of experience it's it's partly a
matter of experience because you have to
be sensitive to where where the
complexities in a problem lie on the
other hand you can practice it so one of
the things that we do in our classes is
we go through a whole series of design
problems and and they're open-ended
right but we put them up on the
whiteboard and then I say so where's our
part yeah and then we have a
conversation with the students and they
the first one that I put up they go what
mm-hmm
I said why the hard part what do you
mean by the hard part and said well
where do you think
you gotta have the biggest struggles to
try to sort out what's going on with
this particular design problem and you
know they come up with various various
suggestions and then we talk it through
and then we do it again and again and
again and again and and that's that's
not a guarantee that they'll understand
it for every single problem that comes
their way but they do learn to ask the
question yeah and that's the important
part right so rather than I mean how
many design teams have you seen or how
many design if students have you seen we
say let's design isn't that two seconds
later they're on the board they're
drawing things and they have never said
where's the hard part yeah or what are
the goals for this particular meeting
why are why are we here what are the
goals for this particular design project
and that's a mindset that you got to
change and that's a mindset even if
you're not a great designer you can
still contribute that design behavior to
a team that is working right you might
be a manager you might not be the best
designer but you might have a design
team that that's awesome and you see
them working and you see that they
forget the write down the khole so you
can say look yeah why don't you write
down the goals and the constraints and
then let's design again and so you can
you can make these kinds of
contributions as long as you're aware of
them I like then of course there's also
some criticism for me on some of the
tips please so some of the tips seem to
be a matter of face to me something like
experts prefer elegant abstraction what
is elegant I'm sure that in a team you
have two solutions and two people in
favor of those solutions will say - more
elegant than yours is this a matter of
faith or or am I wrong here actually
it's ironic we were discussing this over
dinner last night with Brian Randall and
Henry Lawson and we continue to have the
conversation about what elegance is so
yes I believe that the assessment of
elegance may be personal what's typical
of experts is the striving for elegance
the understanding that what they want is
something that is simple that addresses
the essence that that is clearly
expressed that doesn't add extra right
so there is a sense of what elegance is
um the beginning of my PhD work was try
to define elegance with respect to
programming languages
I failed utterly and 30 years later I
still can't give you a definition that I
I you know can stand on a soapbox with
but the striving to elegance to a sense
of elegance I believe is a
characteristic of expert behavior yeah
and it might also relate with experts
keep it simple because I think an
elegant solution is very much also a
simple solution these might be in a
relationship to each other
often so an elegant solution also
communicates how it works yeah right so
when you see it you want to you get it
you get it yeah pipe and filter is sort
of the canonical example right yeah is
you see it once you understand it it
makes complete sense and it's super
elegant and and I think that's that's
the kind of thing that experts will
strive for also some of the insights
seem to be in conflict with each other
so experts prefer solutions they know
versus experts try the opposite can we
unite these or are these just insights
that apply to different situations
they're part of your toolbox right so so
so often when I describe two teams
what's what's going on is you have a
toolbox and you need to pull a certain
tool out in a certain situation right so
experts will borrow existing solutions
and designs in software they will work
really hard to do that because they know
that designing something themselves is a
difficult endeavor and if somebody is
figuring it out and if they can trust it
right that's a big that's a big part of
it they can trust that software they can
trust that design they will use it
however if they're designing and they
get stuck then they might say so what
would happen if we didn't use and reuse
this particular solution and we thought
about it differently so what if we did
the opposite of what we just have been
doing so they're very much compatible
you you they're not goals to achieve
there they're tools that you can use to
get yourself on stuck to go in a
different direction to to play with the
design that you're working on so we
think of them as complementary
because what you're trying to do is work
with them not to take them off yeah but
that leads to a new maybe a higher-level
problem of when to use the right tool so
another of the inside is extras break
the rules so I love breaking the rules
but it's not always a good strategy and
it's very hard to know am I on the right
pad and do I need to break the rules or
should I take into account the
constraints that are here and use
another solution and I already have
how do experts decide which of the tools
to use so so the first thing I would say
is it very often
experts break the rules and the example
in the illustration in the book is let's
pretend there's no gravity as a way to
understand the constraints so there's an
example of how they're complementary but
if you think just to step aside for a
minute into a much broader view in most
disciplines we learn the rule set the
vocabulary the syntax of semantics of
the domain first if you learn too if you
do ballet if you do judo if you learn
music the first thing that you do are
norms right and you learn those and you
practice those until you're really in
the repertoire you do your scales you do
your Kutta you demonstrate that you
understand what these things are and how
they are applied what that gives you is
a grounding and understanding not just
what the rules are but why the rules are
the rules because now you have
experience of these things in practice
then you have the grounds on which to
say okay I want to improvise now when
might I break the rules and for what
effects so now you understand that your
role breaking is purposeful it's not
just let's throw all the rules away it's
actually I want to achieve something
beyond what's here so I'm going to reach
out in a principled way so very often
some of the contrasts are about experts
saying we need something to shift our
thinking a lot of so a lot of the
insights arise from work about the
nature of innovation in high-performing
teams what do they do and they have a
whole collection of practices that are
about getting them to think
imaginatively getting them to generate
ideas getting them to challenge their
own thinking and to reveal their own
assumptions because you actually have to
work pretty hard to do that and very
often it is exactly this stuff that says
let's do something odd let's do
something shocking for a moment
or let's just do something that isn't in
the normal path of narrowing development
so and they include things like stepping
back and saying hold on okay we've been
going down this path it's all going fine
that's fine but have we really
understood the problem correctly now
that we've spent some time with it is
our understanding the problem adequate
so let's go back and review that in the
same way as this constraint is really
problematic we're really not sure what
to do about it this is really taxing us
okay
throw the constraint away what would we
do then does does throwing that
constraint away give us any insight into
how we might address that constraint or
alternatively I'm thrashing I've tried
this twice I'm not getting anywhere I'm
just going to do something else because
if I make progress in something else I
may again have either time to do some
background reasoning about the the thing
I'm stuck on or the Reconstructor that
something else may give me insight into
the thing is troubling me so it's it is
this whole sense that you're not just
arbitrarily breaking rules you're not
arbitrarily throwing everything a way
that you know the patterns the systems
and so on it's much more that you're
using techniques that allow you to see
again or to see differently so but just
interject your question is awesome
though because because what the question
gets at is when do I use which of these
insights right and that that we don't
know right that that actually is in in
so many ways a whole other layer of
research that needs to be done sort of
how do you recognize a team is stuck or
how do you recognize a design is going
in the wrong way or how do you recognize
that we really need yeah another experts
on the team so so what what the
limitation is is we've given you a
vocabulary we've given you that tool
belt but you still need to practice
using it right if I were to give you a
tool belt with a hammer and a
screwdriver and a bunch of other things
and it said okay go go go build this
desk drawer I'm gonna make some mistakes
where the hammer is gonna hit where the
nail wasn't right that practiced that
level of growing up you still have to do
as a designer right it's not like
magically you
sixty-six insights and boom I know how
to do it it's you still have to figure
out when certain certain approaches are
useful and that that's that's part of
becoming more experienced right and
that's where we go back to the student
who or the or the young kid in the
design that's what they did right the
the he he had figured out a way to run
into all sorts of situations and figure
out you know if I did this well that
didn't work but if I did that that did
work and and so you you still have to
learn how to use and when to use them
because you could use these very
disruptively
right you could be in a design meeting
you could say five minutes into it are
we still have an hour orientation right
and did we try the opposite that that's
not good so so the sensitivity of
recognizing when you need to insert
something in a meeting that's an
important part and and and you know we
have a fabulous example of a pair of
designers who were doing a traffic
simulator an educational traffic
simulator and and one of them is a true
whiteboard designer is on the whiteboard
doesn't use the eraser uses his hand to
erase stuff it is at home and the other
one is more the I'll sit back I'll
contribute to it but was sitting on the
chair and they're designing designing
designing in an hour into it she gets
off the one time she got up and she said
there's a car there's a car there's a
car and the other designer meant what
and she said there's a car and what she
meant was we're building this simulation
and you have been working really hard
but you've not modeled a car right and
his assumption was we don't need the
model cars we can actually do this with
an aggregate of how many cars that are
on the road and we'll be fine and she
had figured out that there's a car in
her mind and so finding the timing of
that and figuring out when you actually
say hey you need to reorient yourself
we're missing a part of that that
interplay you know that's that's
something that's a skill that's got to
be developed because when I look at my
undergraduate teams the there's often
one of the undergrads who's very vocal
and who's designing and when somebody
steps in and says hey I think it's like
different dismisses that yeah
and what this person said there's a car
okay let's explore that and that
actually the interesting thing was for
15 minutes they argued and they said no
there's car yes those garden said let's
table that let's design a bunch of other
things and while we're designing these
other things we'll learn whether there
should be a car or not and so that
ability to to postpone the decision to
disagree for a while and let the rest of
the design speak for itself those are
again strategies that come with
experience and and so the book gives you
tools but it's not a substitute for
actually building your experience thanks
so you should do another study to
interview people when they're making
such a remark why did you think this was
the right tool to use that would be nice
for there is a so what's clearly missing
in the book or what isn't addressed is
different domains so it seems to be a
very generic book about so far design I
think lots of the tips could also be
used if you're designing a building or a
chair it's very generic but there are
differences in a domain I would say
designing an iPhone F is quite different
from designing software for a nuclear
power plant for example different
constraints do some of the insights
apply to some of the domains or do you
think the domain isn't important for the
design process it's just another
constraint but let me try to answer it's
it the page so try to answer because
this was interesting right of course
design in different domains is very
different but it's less so whether it's
different in different domains as what
is the nature of the design problem that
I'm facing right so if I'm a software
designer for a nuclear plant and I've
designed 15 of them when number 16 comes
by this might actually be a fairly
routine design problem for me and I
might go about it in a way in a similar
way to an iPhone app designer who has
bill flappy bird and then flappy bird
too and flappy bird three and now meets
the design flappy bird 4 but it's a very
similar kind of design that they're
doing and so we might lean on
using a lot of our existing knowledge a
lot of existing components making sure
that we test things appropriately so we
might go about it actually fairly
similarly in those domains however if I
am new to the iPhone app right and I was
a nuclear plant designer and now I need
to design an iPhone app this is very new
territory to me so I'm going to have to
do a lot of other kinds of strategies
and other kinds of approaches as
compared to the person who has done this
a bunch of times so it to me it's less
so about whether the domains are so
different as it is what what the nature
of the design problem is that I'm
confronted with in terms of my
experience familiarity and complexity of
the design problem that's in front of me
I'd I'd also point out that even though
the different domains have different
objects different constraints different
concerns the thinking process is still
similar the underlying thinking process
still has to do with understanding the
problem understanding your goals and
trying to find appropriate ways to
resolve those in in terms of the
software that you're building so so
andre is talking about normal versus
radical design you know whether we can
use pattern matching we actually have to
reason through new solutions and that
runs all the way through because even
normal versus radical plays through
within designs in terms of the parts we
know about in the parts that are new and
so there may well be within the internal
parts of designing some problems they're
well understood and you have patterns
for that and so you can just take them
for granted on the ones that are not so
familiar that they may be the essential
tough problem that you want to focus on
where you really need to reason about it
and the processes that you bring to both
of those are going to be fairly
consistent processes it still comes back
to design thinking okay what do you
think about the state of the software
industry in terms of design so are we in
a better shape in a better state today
than 20 years ago these are industries
changing also from the design
perspective it used to be maybe more
waterfall and big design up front and
now we're going to agile where we still
do some big
sign up front are we improving as a
community and designing or do we still
have a long way to go you know the it's
it's a fabulous question for where we
are today right so today we are at a
conference where we're some of the
luminaries from from 4050 years ago 30
years ago are actually here and some of
them were fantastic designers the right
we know them because of the kinds of
things that they designed today what
what I want to say is that the the
materials we have that are available to
us as designers are very different right
so so 40 years ago you might say people
had brick and mortar and that's what
they had right today we have cement
steel aluminum carbon and we can we can
build skyscrapers and 40 years ago we
couldn't so so the materials the
components that are available our
understanding of how certain components
fit and don't fit that has really
changed our ability to design more
complex systems more functional systems
more appropriate systems we certainly
have learned a lot through the
experience from 4050 years of what are
some good design methodologies that we
can apply right I think agile is an
encoding of in some ways many of the
practices that that we've learned over
time that lead generally not always but
generally to to a smoother and better
self development process that delivers
better what what the users might want
and might might need but in the end when
you ask are we better designers I think
that's a really interesting question
right I think our population of
designers has grown a lot I think
they're they're still are there's an out
state that a set of outstanding experts
that we've been fortunate to work with
but have we really figured out yet to to
build a practice of apprenticeship of
teaching people how to design and do
that reliably as they're coming through
their computer science and software
engineering and other kind
degree programs I don't I don't think
we've succeeded there yet I do think
that as a whole we certainly advanced
the state of what we can work with and
our understanding of how we can work
with that to to build the system to a
building today but I think one of the
places that we are holding ourselves up
is in the relationship between the
business models the business goals and
the software goals so one of the things
that we see in industry is that there
are companies and and groups that are
not effective in practice but partly
that's about the way they've established
their goal sets and the way they've
established it's not that the individual
developers are not capable of good
design it's that the context in which
they're working constrains them away
from yeah the long term thinking the big
picture thinking the innovation to
immediate you know no immediate results
KPIs and so on and so we hear you know
we keep bumping into people who feel
suppressed by the industry who feel
forced into responsive rather than
principled practice because of the
constraints under which they're working
and I think that understanding the
bigger picture um so for what one of the
things we see in expert teams in
high-performing teams is that they are
socially embedding the kinds of
practices that lead them to good robust
designs innovation and so on right so
they're actually actively building this
culture around design thinking and
around quality and so on right and very
often they are fending off an
organizational push to behave
differently
because potentially management which has
become detached from engineering has
read about something and wants to impose
it I mean so I did a lot of work on UML
some years ago and it was very
interesting that even in companies where
there was an organizational push to
adopt model driven development the
interpretation of model driven
development in the company varied from
team to team and some of that depended
on what authority the team had to do its
own thing without being scrutinized by
measurement and it ranged from people
who were wholehearted adopters and we're
benefiting in the ways they were
benefiting to people who were not
actually adopting it because it didn't
fit what they were doing but they were
actually kind of putting some
documentation together at the end
to satisfy management and it isn't a
judgment on the outcomes but even within
companies with the if the organizational
imperatives are not aligned with and in
dialogue with the kinds of development
qualities that we need and and the
qualities of expert the expert practices
then you might well find things that
aren't optimal so do I summarize it
correct as saying that it's not so much
about teaching people to be better
designers the biggest win we have is to
change organizations so that there's
more room for Design Thinking I think
both I don't think it's an either/or so
there's a wonderful paper by a man named
David Walker called the soup that hole
in the table or something like that
and his argument is fundamentally this
that you need the soup you need
excellent designers right you need the
bowl you need the team that gets them to
work together and optimizes them and
uses them for what they're good at and
you need the table the organization that
gives them the context in which to
operate and I think we actually need to
pay attention to that whole ecosystem
not just to one component on its own
great well that's all the questions I
have thanks a lot for being on the show
is there anything you wanted to add that
we didn't address it's the one question
you can stumped us we I suspect we could
talk about this for a long time yeah I
think so too
I'll have one I really like I sort of
want to toss out a thank you to sort of
all the people that we've been able to
talk to right and the people that have
led us into their organizations when you
know peers to researchers we're from the
academic world and they say you know can
we look at your work for a little while
while you're working and we try not to
criticize you in the process but we're
gonna learn a few things and the number
of practitioners who have who've just
opened up their arms welcomed us and
actually we would like to talk to you
right and that that's but that's been
probably the most gratifying part of it
is is being able to be in dialogue and
then for me the a yeah we wrote the book
fantastic great I'm excited about it
what I'm much more excited about is
being able to go into the classroom
right and say here's what I was doing
last week when I was at this
organization and here's the kind of
stuff we talked about and this is why
it's important that you take this class
and what you need to learn at what you
need to take away especially when in the
beginning of the class I have to tell
them look you're not going to know what
you're going to do possess a design and
in design things are unknown and so I'm
not going to give you a grading rubric
that says if you do this this this and
this you have a great great but you're
gonna have to trust me in this class
that in the end you're gonna get a fine
grade but in the middle I'm gonna give
you all of the feedback that you would
get on the quality of your designs in
the real world and so their score
miserable all along the way but
eventually sort of towards the end of
the corridor semester they start picking
it up because they start understanding
that actually oh he means I really have
to think about this right and I really
actually have to articulate my
assumptions and I really gotta salt the
hard part and then three four or five
years later to be able to go back and
say how's it going and and seeing them
in the organization and then say and
them saying hey that was an important
class that is the stuff that I needed to
know
that's super gratifying and then to be
able to continue that relationship and
say now can I look at your team right is
that that sort of the to me this is an
example of how in the stree and academia
can actually work together where we're
trained in looking for the patterns
you're doing a fantastic job out there
and industry but together we can all
learn from each other and and build up
the field as a whole to to pay attention
to something that is that is truly
fundamental and in some ways still
carries with it a lot of mystique right
is design is what it is never this thing
is this hard thing and and it's not it
is but it's not but it is but there are
ways of thinking about it there's ways
of engaging with it
if you're conscious about your practices
if you really reflect that is important
and and one of the sort of sort of
closing examples that we often use is an
expert software designers in the room
twice so they're there on their own in
the thick of it designing the thing and
somehow they're there as well observing
all of the dynamics of the team and how
they're going about it and and that
interplay of being able to do that and
and to step into that role in and out in
each of those roles in and out that's
really what what distinguishes an expert
from from somebody who who stills making
valuable contributions but can learn
some more things I think another way of
saying that is that what one of the
really gratifying things about working
with industry across countries is how
many genuinely reflective engaged
practitioners there are ok I know I have
dealt with people in academia who think
that practitioners are idiots and
they're lazy and they're ignorant and
that is not what we have found ok as I
say there are often organizational
constraints on what they do but by and
large they are not that and to be
welcomed into someplace by reflective
practitioners who want a chance to think
about what they do and how to make it
better who want to know what other
people are doing that they might adopt
even if they only adopt it on their own
terms which is typical right there's an
awful lot of that going on and so the
key to all of this
someone asked us yesterday what's the
single most important insight that you
have and it's that experts are
reflective and high-performing teams are
reflective and they actually commit
proper time and thought to reflection
it's not just lip service I would say
that's a great end of the show
thanks a lot thanks for being on the
show and we'll make sure all the books
you mentioned and of course also a link
to your own book will be in the show
notes we click on read more if they want
listen thank you for having us it's
great yep thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by out your police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening